字幕出自 Netflix，提前 16 秒对应 BD Subtitles from Netflix, 16 seconds ahead for BD Netflixの字幕、BDは16秒先読 み
字幕出自 Netflix，提前 16 秒对应 BD Subtitles from Netflix, 16 seconds ahead for BD Netflixの字幕、BDは16秒先読 み
Thors!
托尔兹！
Helga!
赫尔加！
YEAR 987 A.D. HJÖRUNGAVÁGR
（公元987年 约龙阿沃格）
What are you doing just standing there?
你呆站在那里做什么？
Are you unwell?
你不舒服吗？
Sorry. I was just resting my eyes.
抱歉 我只是打了个盹
Our formation has spread out too far.
我们的作战阵型太分散了
A second wave would overwhelm us.
这样下去挡不住敌人的第二波袭击
Thorkell, I want you to push the front when Floki comes closer to us.
托鲁克尔 佛洛基接近我们时 我要你去把前线往前推进
That airhead, huh?
那个笨蛋吗？
Well, I'll do it.
嗯 我来吧
What about you?
你呢？
I'll hold them back.
我来拖住敌人
What do you mean?!
那是什么意思？嘿！
How can you do that from there--
你从那里怎么拖…
He sure is nimble.
他确实挺灵活啊
Wait! A solo sneak attack?
等等…单独偷袭？
Maria, I'm sorry…
玛…玛丽亚 对不起…
EPISODE 1: SOMEWHERE FAR AWAY
（第一集：除这里之外的其他地方）
YEAR 1002 A.D. ICELAND
（公元1002年 冰岛）
Oh, Thorfinn. Please feed the sheep and milk the cows.
哦 托尔芬 请你把羊喂了 把牛奶挤了吧
Okay.
好的
With Markland behind us, we sailed further south.
马克兰已经在我们身后 我们进一步向南航行了
"There are richer lands there,"
“还有更富饶的土地”
the wind seemed to say.
风似乎是这么说的
And then, I found it.
然后 我找到了它
A new continent!
一片新大陆！
A new land of bountiful fruit harvests and waves of grassy meadows.
果实丰收、草原波涛汹涌的新土地
I gave the land a name.
我给这片土地起了个名字
I called it
我叫它
"Vinland."
“文兰”
What do you think, you rascals?
你们这些臭小子们觉得如何？
Does that change your view of me? The great Leif Erikson!
这会改变你们对我的看法吗？ 伟大的雷夫埃里克森！
Wow, old man Leif!
哇 雷夫老头！
What then?
然后呢？
-Were there people? -Was it warm?
-那片土地上有人吗？ -那里暖和吗？
Was it bigger than Iceland?
比冰岛大吗？
It was indeed.
的确很温暖
It was much warmer than here.
比这里温暖多了
Grass covered the whole land.
整片土地被草覆盖
We even met the native peoples.
我们甚至见到了当地人
We couldn't communicate with words, but we became fast friends.
我们无法用语言交流 但我们很快就成了朋友
This headdress and this pipe are gifts from them.
这个头饰和这个烟斗 就是他们送的礼物
See this here?
看到这个了吗？
Only a true warrior can wear this upon his head.
只有真正的战士才能把它戴在头上
What's this? The children are still awake?
这是怎么回事？ 孩子们还醒着？
-Let me touch it, old man! -I'm sorry.
-让我摸一下吧 老头！ -对不起
I wanted to let them listen to Leif's story.
我想让他们听听雷夫的故事
A true warrior, huh?
真正的战士 是吗？
You really are amazing!
你真的好厉害！
Aren't I? You're a good boy, Thorfinn.
是吧？托尔芬 你是个好孩子
When you're older, would you like to sail on my ship?
等你再大点 愿不愿意 坐我的船跟我去远航？
What? Let me go with you now!
什么？现在就让我跟你去吧！
Now?
现在？
But something is strange, Leif.
可有件事很奇怪 雷夫
My grandpa told me.
我爷爷亲自告诉我的
Jörmungandr is to the west, and it eats any boat that comes near it.
海蛇耶梦加得在西边 只要有船接近它 它就会把他们吞噬
And beyond that, nothing else exists.
除那之外 没有别的东西存在
That's precisely why
正因为如此
you should realize how impressive I am!
你才应该意识到我有多厉害！
See? This proves that I am a true warrior.
看到了吗？ 这证明我是真正的战士
But Leif, you're not even a warrior.
可是雷夫 你连战士都不是啊
You don't get it, do you?
你还是不懂 对吧？
Merely going to war doesn't make you a warrior!
光是参加战争并不能说明你是战士！
To sail a ship is to fight the sea.
驾驶一艘船远航 就是和大海做斗争
Isn't that amazing?
难道那不厉害吗？
-Just as I thought. -Yeah.
-跟我想的一样 -对
What?
什么？
Everyone says you're just a child with a beard.
大家都说你只是个留着胡子的小孩
You only explore but you're useless in battle.
你只不过是在探索而已 打仗时你根本派不上用场
Others speak for you?
你这只是在人云亦云
Thorfinn, you believe me, don't you?
托尔芬 你相信我的 对吧？
Or is it that
还是说
you can't believe an old adventurer who doesn't gone to war?
你无法相信一个不打仗的 老探险家的话？
If my dad said you were a warrior, then I would believe it, but…
如果我爸说他是个战士 那我就相信 可是…
Thors!
托尔兹！
These kids are mocking me! Set them straight!
这些孩子在嘲笑我！让他们停下！
All right. That's enough for today.
好了 今天就到这里吧
Ari, take the kids home please.
亚雷 把孩子们带回家吧
Okay, Thors.
好的 托尔兹
Bye!
再见！
I see.
原来如此
They froze to death in Greenland…
他们在格陵兰岛被冻死了…
The cold waves this year are especially severe.
今年的寒潮特别严重
Much of the livestock will die, too.
很多家畜也会死掉
But the problem is that with each year, the cold becomes ever harsher.
可问题是
It's so cold.
好冷啊…
Welcome back.
欢迎回来
Only these two were a little weak.
只有这两只有点虚弱
You must've been freezing out there, Ylva!
攸尔法 你在外面一定冻死了吧！
Let me warm you up.
我来给你暖暖
You perverted old man!
你这个变态老头！
Mother, go to sleep. You'll catch another cold.
妈妈 去睡觉吧 否则又会感冒的
I will be fine.
我没事
-Come help me tie up the sheep. -Okay.
-来帮我把羊绑起来 -好
It seems things are rough here, too.
看来这里也很不容易啊
Yeah.
是的
Sooner or later, there may come a winter that no one can survive.
无人能熬过去的冬天迟早会到来
At home, my younger brother is making plans to migrate.
在家里 我弟弟正在计划迁移
It's far, isn't it?
很远 是吧？
Come now.
哪里的话
I made a round trip.
我这不是去了又回来了吗？
Forward!
前进！
Vinland is just over yonder!
文兰就在那边！
Captain Thorfinn!
托尔芬船长！
What is it?
什么事？
It's the Jörmungandr!
是耶梦加得！
I'll take you on, beast!
我来对付你 野兽！
It hurts.
好痛…
Ylva! Go to your own bed! You're crowding me!
攸尔法！去你自己的床睡！ 你挤死我了！
What? I don't want to.
什么？我不想去
That's not fair!
这不公平！
I warmed this bed up!
是我把这张床焐暖和的…
They're still talking.
他们…还在聊天啊
Don't worry about it.
别担心
Leave the worrying to the adults.
让大人们去担心吧
Anyway, come here.
不管怎样 先到这边来
I'll give you a nice, warm hug!
我来给你个温暖的拥抱
Goodness.
天啊…
Hey, Father! Let's buy a slave?
嘿 父亲！咱们为何不买个奴隶呢？
Mother's not in good health, and I'm always busy helping her.
母亲身体不好 所以我总是忙着帮她…
We do things differently.
我们不那么做事的
Stop asking.
别每年都问这个
You're so strange.
你这人真奇怪
Ylva!
攸尔法！
I thought I was going to die.
我以为我要死了呢
-Are you hurt? -No.
-你受伤了吗？ -没有
What's wrong?
怎么了？
There's something underneath.
底下有什么东西…
Ylva?
攸尔法？
Hey, old man.
嘿 老头
How much of last night's story was true?
昨晚的故事有多少是真的？
"How much"? It's all true.
你说“多少”是什么意思？全是真的啊
Then let me sail with you.
那就让我搭你的船吧
-I'll believe you when I see it myself. -Fool.
等我亲眼看到 就会相信你
You can't say that just to get on the ship.
别只为了上船才说你相信
If you really want to sail go with your father.
如果你这么想乘船 让你父亲带你
Look. That's a battleship.
看 那边有一艘战舰
The village has used it for generations,
村子里几代人都用过了
but they'd gladly lend it to your father.
可我肯定他们会很乐意 把船借给你父亲的
My father's stingy. No matter how many times I ask, he says no.
我父亲很小气 不管我 问多少次 他都拒绝我
He's not stingy.
他这不是小气
That sea out there, Thorfinn, is frightening.
托尔芬 外面的大海很吓人
When I was young, I was once trapped by an ice floe.
我小时候曾经被浮冰困住
It was right after we moved to Greenland.
就是在我们搬到格陵兰之后
We were reckless.
我们当时很鲁莽
Our provisions depleted quickly.
我们的补给很快就耗尽了
We ate ice to distract ourselves from starvation.
只能吃冰块来分散对饥饿的注意力
At last, the ship was crushed by the ice,
最后 船被冰山压碎了
Before I knew it, I was alone.
不知不觉间 就只剩我一个人了
All six of my companions had died.
我的六个同伴都死了
Why?
为什么？
Why did we struggle so hard just to live on these northern islands?
为什么我们这么辛苦地挣扎 只为了在这些北方岛屿上生活呢？
Helga! Boil some water!
赫尔加！烧点水！
Ylva, bring the furs.
攸尔法 把皮草拿来
Okay.
好的
Oh dear. What happened?
哦 天啊 怎么了？
He was buried in the snow.
他被埋在雪里了
That looks so painful.
看起来好痛苦
What happened to him?
他怎么了？
-Stoke the fire. -Okay.
-烧火 -好的
Hey, Father.
嘿 父亲
Isn't he already dead?
他不是已经死了吗？
His limbs are rotting.
他的四肢正在腐烂啊
Besides, this could be bad.
而且 这可能是件坏事呢
He's…
他…
He's not from this village.
他不是这村里的人
Poor thing.
可怜的家伙
What was he doing out in that blizzard?
他在暴风雪里做什么？
"What was he doing?"
“他在做什么？”
He's a runaway slave.
他是个逃跑的奴隶
Sheltering him could be trouble for us.
庇护他可能会给我们带来麻烦
We were running away.
我们当时在逃跑
Our ancestors lived further east.
我们的祖先住在更东边
They lived in a land called Norway.
他们住在一片叫做挪威的土地上
It's warmer than here, and the sea doesn't freeze.
那里比这里温暖 大海不会结冰
A beautiful land protected by many fjords.
一片被许多峡湾保护着的美丽土地
But one day,
可是有一天
a strong man named Harald appeared.
一名叫做哈拉尔的强者出现了
Harald's forces burned through villages on their conquests,
哈拉尔的军队在征服的过程中 对一个个村庄进行烧杀
and he proclaimed himself the first king of a unified Norway.
他宣布自己是统一挪威的第一位国王
And he forced the people to choose.
他逼迫百姓选择
Obey the king or leave Norway.
服从国王 或者离开挪威
Many despised Harald's tyranny and left to a faraway land far from oppression.
很多人对哈拉尔的暴政充满鄙视
That land is here, Iceland.
那片土地就是这里 冰岛
You're lying.
你骗人
You're just a liar after all!
你只不过是个骗子！
My father and my ancestors would never run away like that!
我父亲和祖先绝不会那样逃走！
You foolish geezer!
你这个愚蠢的老头！
Washed-up explorer!
没用的探险家！
Father!
父亲！
Father, listen.
父亲 听着
Old man Leif said…
雷夫老头说…
Welcome home, Thorfinn.
欢迎回家 托尔芬
Who is that?
那是谁？
A slave from somewhere else. He's a runaway.
从别的地方来的奴隶 他是逃跑的
He woke up!
他醒过来了！
Can you tell me your name?
嘿 你能告诉我你的名字吗？
It's cold.
好冷…
The fire! Ylva, stoke it more.
火！攸尔法 把它烧得更猛点
Okay.
好…好的
Where did you come from?
你是从哪里来的？
W-Will I…
我…我会被…
be sent back?
送回去吗？
To Halfdan's… home…
送回哈夫丹的…家里吗…
Halfdan?
哈夫丹？
So you are from beyond the mountains?
所以你是从山上过来的？
I hate that place.
我讨厌那个地方
I hate it.
我讨厌…
But…
但是…
I have…
我…
nowhere else to go.
没有别的地方可以去了…
Thors!
托尔兹！
Come quickly. Halfdan's at the harbor!
快来 哈夫丹就在港口！
He brought his men and they're blaming us for something.
他带了人过来 因为什么事情怪我们
Only you can face him!
除了你 没人能面对他
They want to know about a slave and forced their way on land.
他们要求找出一个奴隶的下落 他们强行上岸了
Leif is holding him back,
雷夫正挡着他们
but a fight could break out at any moment!
可是战斗随时可能爆发！
Please, come fast!
求你了 跟我来吧！
Chains are the only adornment that suits a man's neck.
锁链是唯一适合人脖子的装饰
Not gold, not silver,
不能是黄金链 不能是银链
but iron chains.
只能是铁链
Only a chained neck
只有被链子锁住的脖子
can make a man more civilized.
才能让这个人更体面
Don't you think?
你不觉得吗？
Last night, one of my slaves broke his chain and escaped.
昨夜 我的一个奴隶锯断铁链 跑了
Any idea where he could be?
你知道他可能会在哪儿吗？
Don't pick a fight with us!
别想跟我们找茬！
You're just trying to bring up an old quarrel!
你这是为了之前的事来的吧！
He's always having disagreements with us.
他总是跟我们意见不合
We had an intervention last time.
上次我们有人介入
Brat. I remember you.
臭小子 我记得你
You cut off my left arm during that fight!
上次打架的时候 你把我的左臂砍了
Speak for yourself.
那只是你觉得
How dare you cut off my elder brother's leg!
你怎么敢把我哥哥的腿砍了！
That's enough, Ari!
亚雷 够了！
My brother will never walk again!
我哥哥再也不能走路了！
I'll slice off your leg too!
我也要把你的腿砍下来！
Come at me!
放马过来吧！
Your people and your laws mean nothing!
你们的人和你们的法律都是狗屎！
Halfdan.
哈夫丹…
I'll chain you up, bastard.
我要把你用链子拴起来 混蛋
Anyone who mocks the law is unforgivable.
任何嘲弄法律的人都是不可原谅的
The law is the chain.
锁链就是法律
When brutes are chained, they become men for the first time.
畜生被锁链拴住才能第一次变成人
Do not forget that.
这一点别忘了
The runaway is a young Slavic man.
逃跑者是个年轻的斯拉夫人
Any idea where he is?
知道他在哪里吗？
Where am I?
我在哪里？
This is the first time I've felt so at peace.
我第一次感到如此平静
Stay with us! Hold on!
别死啊！嘿 撑住！
Keep conscious or else you'll die!
保持清醒 否则你会死的！
Thors.
托尔兹…
Father.
父亲…
Mother.
母亲…
Sister.
还有姐姐…
You are all here?
你们都在这里？
I was worried.
我担心死了
Each of us was sold alone.
我们都是分开被卖掉的
Where is this place?
这是什么地方？
Why am I…
我为什么…
Far to the west
在西边遥远的地方
and beyond the sea
越过大海
is a land called Vinland.
有一个叫文兰的地方
It is a warm…
那是一片温暖
plentiful far away place
肥美的土地
How about it?
怎么样？
Would you like to live there with us someday?
你想有一天跟我们一起住在那里吗？
Vinland.
文兰…
I see.
我明白了
This place
这个地方
is called Vinland.
叫做文兰…
Found him.
找到他了
Forgive the ruckus, Thors.
打扰你了 托尔兹
I am the legitimate owner of that slave.
我是那个奴隶的合法主人
Return him to me.
把他还给我
F-Father…
父…父亲…
Come along, Thorfinn.
来吧 托尔芬
Halfdan!
哈夫丹！
We can explain.
我们可以解释
We weren't hiding him.
我们不是要藏他
Actually, we saved your slave from near death.
实际上 我们把你的奴隶 从濒死边缘救了回来
Halfdan. How much did you pay for this man?
哈夫丹 你买这个人花了多少钱？
F-Father,
父…父亲…
it's rude to ask such a question.
问这种问题很没礼貌
Two young ewes.
两只年轻的母羊
I'll give you three. I will buy him.
那我给你三只 我要买下他
How about it, Halfdan?
怎么样 哈夫丹？
I will be taking him home with me.
我要带他跟我回家
I must make an example of him to the other slaves.
我必须在其他奴隶面前拿他做例子
Then I'll pay you four.
那我给你四只羊
Bastard! Do you not understand what Master Halfdan is saying?
混蛋！ 你不明白哈夫丹大人 在说什么吗…
Silence.
闭嘴
And if I ask for double that?
如果我要你开价的两倍呢？
I'll pay it.
我会付的
All males under three years old.
八只羊都会是三岁以下的公羊
Eight sheep for this worthless bastard.
用八只羊买这个没用的混蛋
A good deal.
很划算
No way. It's settled?
不会吧 谈妥了？
Thors.
托尔兹
Do you plan to free him from his chains?
你打算把他从锁链中解救出来吗？
Where will you take him then?
那你要带他去哪里？
I'll choose the sheep myself.
羊得由我来选
Ylva, are you sad?
攸尔法 你难过吗？
Of course I am!
当然了！
He gave away eight sheep and the man died anyway!
他白送了八只羊 结果那人还死了！
You idiot, Father!
你是个笨蛋 父亲！
Why are you so strange?
你怎么这么奇怪？
Father.
父亲
Did we run away too?
我们之前也是逃跑的吗？
Old man Leif said our ancestors ran away from the east.
雷夫老头说我们的祖先 是从东边逃跑的
He said they ran away and came here.
他说他们逃跑了 然后来到了这里
Yes.
没错
That is what has been told.
确实有这么个说法
Then…
那么…
if people want to escape here too…
如果人们也想逃离这里
where do they go?
他们该去哪里呢？